{
  "reference_number": "11880",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I have grave doubts about success but happy you are taking it seriously. See NZ govt stats online for \"New Zealandâ€™s net greenhouse\n gas emissions have increased 54 percent since 1990\". Any choice now is OK so long as you measure up against it and consider\n\n tightening it up later."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Don't trust foreign carbon units. Also if I am ight and NZ fails they will just be a drastic cost for no advantage. If we are to give\n foreigners money do so by bribing third world countries to stop destroying native forest."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "self evident"
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "seems rational. will require all party support."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Rather pointless since NZ govt has a history of totally missing climate change targets. maybe link minister's pensions to missing\n targets?"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I am concerned about internation air and sea travel climate change impacts. Unable to find out how it is dealt with by NZ proposed\n policy. Representing about 10% of CO2 output it must be tackled. How about recording either all arriving or all departing\n\n flights/voyages (the former being easier to manage). Has a serious impact on tourism - NZ needs to move from cheap high-volume to\n high-value low volume tourism."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Essential. In fact the most important fact. Please read Prof Jim Fynn's great book and try arguing with his conclusion."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I've read page 47 buty I can't see what you are talking about."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I am concerned about internation air and sea travel climate change impacts. Unable to find out how it is dealt with by NZ proposed\npolicy. Representing about 10% of CO2 output it must be tackled. How about recording either all arriving or all departing\n\nflights/voyages (the former being easier to manage). Has a serious impact on tourism - NZ needs to move from cheap high-volume to\nhigh-value low volume tourism. I would love to give an analysis of the political bureaucratic speak in the govt info published online.\n\nOther than to tell you that this kind of babble is self-defeating I will resist it. Please read \"No Place to Hide: Climate Change - A short\nintroduction for New Zealanders\"; it will improve your ability with English language and clarify your understanding of a very complex\n\nmatter."
    }
  ]
}
